<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article>
    
    <h1>Computer-Aided Translation (CAT) Tools</h1>
    
    <div class="row">
        
        <div class="col-sm-8">
            <!-- Wide left hand column -->
            
            <h3>About CAT Tools</h3>
            <p>84000 currently uses SmartCAT, a computer-assisted translation web tool for individual or collaborative translation. Computer-assisted translation software can be used to create and manage translation memories of terms and phrases, or even simple sentences, throughout one or a collection of translations. This can lead to more consistent terminology in translations and save time and effort by splitting the source text into segments and displaying them in-line with translation memories. CAT tool software also offers project management tools, advanced search functions, version control, and collaboration tools. </p>
            <hr/>
            
            <h3>Three Ways to Use SmartCAT</h3>
            <h4>As a Reference Tool</h4>
            <p>Once you have joined the 84000 account (see instructions below), you will have convenient access to 84000's glossary and translation memories in-line with your Tibetan text, even if you prefer to do your translation elsewhere.</p>
            <h4>Join a Project on the 84000 Account</h4>
            <p>Suggested texts for the 2018 grant cycle are already uploaded to SmartCAT. You can email 84000smartCAT@gmail.com to request to join any project currently posted. You can also email a request for any other Kangyur text to be uploaded. See the tutorials below for details.</p>
            
            <h4>Create Your Own Project from a Personal or Team Account</h4>
            <p>See the tutorials below to learn how to create your own translation projects from scratch and how to create and manage your own team account.</p>
            <p>If you are already using CAT tools, you can download the glossary and TMX files from the right-hand column on this page.</p>
            <hr/>
            <h3>Getting Started</h3>
            <p>For details on getting started and working in SmartCAT, see the tutorials below. Here are the basics:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>Create an account at <a href="https://www.smartcat.ai/" target="smartcat">smartcat.ai</a>.
                </li>
                <li>Email 84000smartCAT@gmail.com for an invite to the 84000 account.</li>
                <li>It is optional but recommended that you upload the 84000 Cumulative Glossary and translation memories (TMX files), which can be downloaded from the right-hand column on this page. This will give you more convenient access to the dictionary from the translation workspace on the SmartCAT platform.</li>
            </ol>
            <hr/>
            <h3>Videos</h3>
                
                <p>A general introduction to working with Tibetan in SmartCAT.</p>
            <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9">
                <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vfELrgSlms0?ecver=1" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media"/>
            </div>
            <hr/>
            <p>A six-part series of tutorials specific to working with 84000 texts in SmartCAT. You can find a playlist and navigate the tutorials by clicking the three-line icon in the upper-left corner of the video window.</p>
            <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9">
                <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PLmbvKjjf-ogF7CxjiA0KBkghbxqn5ZZsB" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media"/>
            </div>
            <hr/>
            <h3>General Guides to SmartCAT</h3>
            <p>Finally, here are some general tutorials for using SmartCAT in any language.</p>
            <l>
                <li>
                    <a href="https://community.smartcat.ai/articles/freelancer-essentials/" target="freelancer">Freelancer Essentials</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="https://community.smartcat.ai/articles/tutorials/" target="tutorials">Tips and Tricks</a>
                </li>
            </l>
     
        </div>
        
        <div class="col-sm-offset-1 col-sm-3">
            <!-- Narrow right hand column --> 
            <h3>Links</h3>
            <l>
                <li>
                    <a href="https://www.smartcat.ai/" target="smartcat">SmartCAT</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="https://github.com/Esukhia/derge-kangyur" target="ekangyur">eKangyur</a>: See under <a href="http://translator-tools.84000-translate.org/index.html?tab=resources#panelLinks" target="links">resource links</a> for brief instructions.
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="http://www.buddism.ru/ocr/" target="buddhism-ocr">Tibetan OCR</a>: Convert PDF, TIFF, or JPG images into editable and searchable text.
                </li>
            </l>
            <hr/>
            <h3>Downloads</h3>
            
                <p>Glossary files</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                    <a href="/data/Cumulative%20Glossary-NoDup.xlsx">Cumulative Glossary–No Duplicates</a>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <a href="/data/Cumulative%20Glossary-Full.xlsx">Cumulative Glossary–Full</a>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <a href="/data/cumulative-glossary.xml">Cumulative Glossary XML</a>
                </li>
                </ul>
                <p>TMX Files</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <a href="/data/Toh%2083.tmx">Toh. 83</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="/data/Toh%2085.tmx">Toh. 85</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="/data/Toh%2086.tmx">Toh. 86</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <a href="/data/Toh%20100.tmx">Toh. 100</a>
                </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="/data/Toh%20300.tmx">Toh. 300</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                    <a href="/data/Toh%20431.tmx">Toh. 431</a>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <a href="/data/Toh%20544.tmx">Toh. 544</a>
                </li>
                </ul>
            <p>PDF</p>
                <ul>
                <li>
                    <a href="/data/CAT%20and%20Tibetan%20Language.pdf">TM &amp; CAT Tools for Tibetan</a>
                </li>
            </ul>
            <hr/>
            <h3>Volunteer</h3>
            <p>84000 is seeking volunteers to input translation memories for its published texts.</p> 
                <p>Email 84000smartCAT@gmail.com for more info or to volunteer.</p>
            <hr/>
            <h3>Help</h3>
            <p>For assistance with CAT issues email 84000smartCAT@gmail.com</p>
        </div>
    </div>
</article>