<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<texts xmlns="http://read.84000.co/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
    
    <item key="glossary.term-empty-sa-ltn">—</item>
    <item key="glossary.term-empty-bo-ltn">—</item>
    
    <item key="translation-status-group.published.label">Published</item>
    <item key="translation-status-group.translated.label">Translated</item>
    <item key="translation-status-group.in-translation.label">In translation</item>
    <item key="translation-status-group.remaining.label">Not started</item>
    
    <item key="cumulative-glossary.disclaimer">Please bear in mind that we are constantly revising the glossaries and we will continue to
        add more glossaries as we publish translations. To keep up to date please regularly download the latest version from the website. </item>
    
    <item key="source.folio.ekangyur-description-title">About the eKangyur</item>
    <item key="source.folio.ekangyur-description-content">
        <p>The Tibetan page displayed here is from the eKangyur, a digital input version made by the University of Virginia and the British
            Library, with help from Esukhia, from scans of the Degé Kangyur held in the U.S. Library of Congress. This post <span class="text-wy">par phud</span> print (<a href="https://www.tbrc.org/#!rid=W4CZ5369" target="_blank">BDRC catalogue no.
                    W4CZ5369</a>) was purchased in Beijing and brought to the U.S. by William Rockhill in 1908-9.</p>
        <p>Note that 84000 translations are made from a variety of sources, and readings may not always follow this particular version
            exactly. For details of the readings used in this translation, see Introduction and Notes; for the eKangyur, see the <a href="http://www.thlib.org/encyclopedias/literary/canons/about/wiki/tibetan%20canons%20introduction.html#!essay=/stanley/tibcanons/s/b3/" target="_blank">Tibetan and Himalayan Library</a>.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="source.folio.etengyur-description-title">About the eTengyur</item>
    <item key="source.folio.etengyur-description-content">
        <p>The Tibetan page displayed here is from the eTengyur, a digital input version prepared by Esukhia and Barom Theksum Choling. It is based on scans of the Degé Tengyur from Sakya College, completed with the Degé Tengyur from Songtsen Library (<a href="https://library.bdrc.io/show/bdr:MW2KG209989" target="_blank">BDRC catalogue no. W2KG209989</a>).</p>
        <p>Note that 84000 translations are made from a variety of sources, and readings may not always follow this particular version exactly. For details of the readings used in this translation, see Introduction and Notes; for the eTengyur, see the <a href="http://www.thlib.org/encyclopedias/literary/canons/about/wiki/tibetan%20canons%20introduction.html#!essay=/stanley/tibcanons/s/b3/" target="_blank">Tibetan and Himalayan Library</a>.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="source.folio.backlink-label">
        <span>The English translation of this folio by <span class="title">84000 - Translating the words of the Buddha</span> can be found
            at:</span>
    </item>
    
    <item key="translation.print-version">
        <p>This print version was generated at #CurrentDateTime from the online version of the text available on that date. If some time has
            elapsed since then, this version may have been superseded, as most of 84000’s published translations undergo significant updates
            from time to time. For the latest online version, with bilingual display, interactive glossary entries and notes, and a variety
            of further download options, please see <br/>
            <a href="#canonicalHTML" class="printable">#canonicalHTML</a>.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="translation.partial-text-warning">This rendering does not include the entire published text</item>
    <item key="translation.partial-text-link">The full text is available to download as pdf at:</item>
    
    <item key="section.ebook-help-title">Help for downloading eBooks</item>
    <item key="section.ebook-help-body">
        <p>There are many ways to get eBooks onto eReader devices. If you already have a reliable method for this, please simply download
            the texts.</p>
        <p>However, some devices, such as Amazon Kindle, are optimised for downloading books from their associated store, and getting free
            books from other sources on to them can be tricky. Most eReaders have a built in web-browser and we have found this to be the
            simplest way to get free eBooks on to our devices.</p>
        <ol>
            <li>Open the browser on your device. (On a Kindle this is “Beta-Browser” under the main menu).</li>
            <li>Use the browser to go to http://read.84000.co</li>
            <li>Select “View All Translated Texts.”</li>
            <li>Select the “Download AZW3” option for the text you would like to read.</li>
        </ol>
        <p>Unfortunately we cannot test our publications on every device. We try to ensure our texts are readable on as many devices as
            possible by complying with open standards. If you have any feedback about this functionality, or tips for reading them on your
            device, please contact us at <a href="mailto:info@84000.co">info@84000.co</a>.</p>
    </item>

    <!-- About -->
    <item key="about.common.sponsor-button-label">Sponsor a page now </item>
    <item key="about.common.sponsor-button-link">#commsSiteUrl/sponsor-a-page</item>
    <item key="about.common.sharing-label">Share this page:</item>
    <item key="about.common.summary-label">Summary</item>
    <item key="about.common.no-results-label">There are currently not texts in this list</item>
    <item key="about.common.column-toh-label">Toh</item>
    <item key="about.common.column-title-label">Title</item>
    <item key="about.common.column-status-label">Status</item>
    <item key="about.common.column-pages-label">Pages</item>
    <item key="about.common.page-total-label">Total pages:</item>
    <item key="about.common.pages-label">pages</item>
    <item key="about.common.texts-label">texts</item>

    <!-- Progress -->
    <item key="about.progress.header-img-src">#feSiteUrl/imgs/about-headers/progress.jpg</item>
    <item key="about.progress.page-quote">"You should know first hand how Dharma helps you… With this mind if you extend your intention to
        reach out with your translation…it’ll really make a difference in the world, and it already does."</item>
    <item key="about.progress.page-quote-author">Dzigar Kongtrül Rinpoche</item>
    <item key="about.progress.page-intro">
        <p>In 2009, it was determined that only 5% of the Canon had ever been translated into a language spoken today. Working first on the Kangyur, we have raised that figure to almost 10%, and are on track to reach our 2035 target for the complete translation and publication of the Kangyur’s 70,000 pages.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.progress.kangyur-summary-heading">Progress on our 25 year goal to translate the Kangyur</item>
    <item key="about.progress.combined-summary-heading">Progress on our 100 year goal to translate the Kangyur and Tengyur</item>
    <item key="about.progress.outlook">
        <p>Once the Kangyur is complete, the remaining 75 years of our project will be dedicated to the translation and online publication of the 161,800 pages of the Tengyur.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.progress.translations-published-label">Published Translations</item>
    <item key="about.progress.translations-awaiting-label">Translations Awaiting Publication</item>
    <item key="about.progress.translations-remaining-label">Other Translations In Progress</item>
    <item key="about.progress.context-label">completed</item>
    <item key="about.progress.related-pages">
        <h2>Other Related Pages</h2>
        <ul class="list-unstyled">
            <li>
                <a href="#commsSiteUrl/about/work-flow">Learn more about what it takes to produce a page of translation</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#commsSiteUrl/facts-and-figures-about-kangyur-and-tengyur">Learn more about the Kangyur, the Tengyur, and their contents</a>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </item>

    <!-- Impact -->
    <item key="about.impact.header-img-src">#feSiteUrl/imgs/about-headers/impact.jpg</item>
    <item key="about.impact.page-quote">“It’s not just the heritage of one tradition, one civilization or one nation – it’s the heritage of
        the world. The Kangyur and Tengyur will really contribute to the happiness, peace and freedom of all mankind.”</item>
    <item key="about.impact.page-quote-author">Tulku Pema Wangyal Rinpoche</item>
    <item key="about.impact.page-intro">
        <p>Canonical texts have been the source of Buddhist traditions over the centuries. To have the entire Tibetan Buddhist Canon in English has the potential to transform the way we view, study, reference, and practice Buddhist philosophy, history, and its teachings. Imagine if our understanding of the Bible was still mediated through the handful of people who could read Aramaic?</p>
        <p>By 2035, we will complete the translation and publication of the Kangyur. The last time this body of texts was translated into another language was an initiative that began in 900 AD.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.visitors-per-week-stat">
        <div class="heading">Visitors</div>
        <div class="data">
            <span>#visitorsPerWeekFormatted</span> per week</div>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.visitors-description">
        <p>Our online Reading Room - a digital library of English language translations of the words of the Buddha - sees over #visitorsPerWeekFormatted visitors every week.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.reach-countries-stat">
        <div class="heading">Reach</div>
        <div class="data">
            <span>#reachCountriesFormatted</span> countries</div>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.reach-description">
        <p>Our site is regularly visited by people from over #reachCountriesFormatted countries around the world.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.engagement-minutes-stat">
        <div class="heading">Engagement</div>
        <div class="data">
            <span>#annualDownloadsFormatted</span> downloads</div>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.engagement-description">
        <p>In 2020 alone, our readers downloaded #annualDownloadsFormatted sūtras from our online Reading Room.</p>
    </item>
    <!--<item key="about.impact.popular-views-stat">
        <div class="heading">Most popular</div>
        <div class="data">
            <span>#topTextViewsFormatted</span> views of the top 5 sūtras</div>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.popular-description">
        <p>To date in 2018, the following five sūtras have received a combined 43,610 views, out of the almost 150,000 views of our Reading
            Room this year:</p>
        <ol>
            <li>
                <a href="#readingRoomSiteUrl/translation/UT22084-055-001.html">The King of Samādhis Sūtra</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#readingRoomSiteUrl/translation/UT22084-031-002.html">The Transcendent Perfection of Wisdom in Ten Thousand Lines</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#readingRoomSiteUrl/translation/UT22084-060-005.html">The Teaching of Vimalakīrti</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#readingRoomSiteUrl/translation/UT22084-062-010.html">The Rice Seedling</a>
            </li>
            <li>
                <a href="#readingRoomSiteUrl/translation/UT22084-062-012.html">The Sūtra on Dependent Arising</a>
            </li>
        </ol>
        <p>With over 21,000 pages currently in translation, we look forward to giving free access to, and easy readability of, more sūtras
            to you soon.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.impact.countries-title">Countries where our readers come from</item>
    <item key="about.impact.countries-legend">*The flags above are selected examples of the countries where our readers come from. The list
        is not exhaustive.</item>
    <item key="about.impact.countries-timestamp">Information updated on: Aug 5, 2018</item>-->

    <!-- Sponsors -->
    <item key="about.sponsors.header-img-src">#feSiteUrl/imgs/about-headers/sponsors.jpg</item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.page-quote">“Both the very generous benefactors and also the very knowledgeable and experienced translators
        will be able to perfect their two accumulations of virtue through their interdependent connection.”</item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.page-quote-author">Tri Ralpachen (one of the three Dharma kings of Tibet)</item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.page-intro">
        <p>84000 is dependent on the kind and generous support of thousands of donors, many of whom give through our <a href="#commsSiteUrl/sponsor-a-page">Sponsor a Page</a> and <a href="#commsSiteUrl/download-dana">Download Dāna</a> streams,
            as well as through the programs listed below. We are grateful for every offering and believe each to be a gift that is an
            equally meritorious drop in in the ocean of our activity.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.matching-funds-title">Matching Funds Sponsors</item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.sutras-title">Sūtra Sponsors</item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.founding-title">Founding Sponsors</item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.matching-funds-description">
        <p>The Matching Funds Program is designed to incentivize small-dollar donors to give to 84000 on a recurring basis by offering to
            match those donations dollar-for-dollar. We would like to thank the following Matching Funds sponsors for their gift to 84000
            and their generosity in allowing small-dollar donors to feel their contribution is making a more significant impact on the
            progress of the translation of the Tibetan Buddhist canon.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.matching-funds-list-title">
        Our Matching Funds Sponsors
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.sponsor-sutras-link">#readingRoomSiteUrl/about/sponsor-a-sutra.html</item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.sutras-description">
        <p>Every year, we commission a new batch of translations. Some of the designated texts are long, important sūtras that require a
            sizeable amount of funding in order to see the translation process through to completion. We would like to thank our sponsors
            for their generous support of the <a href="#readingRoomSiteUrl/about/sponsor-a-sutra.html">“Sponsor A Sūtra”</a> program.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.sutras-list-title">
        Our Sūtra Sponsors
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.founding-description">
        <p>We would like to thank the 108 Founding Sponsors who so generously provided the seed funding to help 84000 get started with its
            task of translating the words of the Buddha. Each of these sponsors gave or pledged to give between $50,000-$250,000 to help us
            begin our journey. In addition to providing the funding for the initial rounds of translations, the funds are being used or have
            been used to: create the infrastructure for reviewing, editing, and pre-publication work; develop the tools and resources
            necessary for translation work; train translators and editors; and offset both the costs of the initial planning, and the
            current and ongoing administrative and operating costs.</p>
        <p>With the vision and generosity of these Founding Sponsors, 84000 has been able to successfully launch and significantly progress
            with the immense task of translating the words of the Buddha. We offer our heartfelt thanks to all our Founding Sponsors for
            enabling us to safeguard this invaluable world heritage, and making it available for generations to come.</p>
        <p>Dzongsar Khyentse Rinpoche, chairperson of 84000, has written <a href="#commsSiteUrl/message-to-founding-sponsors">a message
                addressed to all 108 Founding Sponsors</a>.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.founding-list-title">
        Our 108 Founding Sponsors
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsors.text-sponsorship-link-label">There are further sponsorship opportunities for this translation</item>

    <!-- Translators -->
    <item key="about.translators.header-img-src">#feSiteUrl/imgs/about-headers/translators.jpg</item>
    <item key="about.translators.page-quote">“It’s very important that translators really come together as one harmonious unit to do the
        work for the present time and also for future generations.”</item>
    <item key="about.translators.page-quote-author">Dzigar Kongtrül Rinpoche</item>
    <item key="about.translators.page-intro">
        <p>84000 awards project-specific grants to teams of translators, editors, and consultants in order to facilitate the
            efficient translation of texts in the Tibetan Buddhist Canon. These teams are external grantees of 84000 whose work is
            considered integral to the fulfillment of our vision.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.translators.lists-title">84000 Translators</item>
    <item key="about.translators.summary-title">Summary</item>
    <item key="about.translators.team-count-label">Number of Teams</item>
    <item key="about.translators.teams-label">teams</item>
    <item key="about.translators.translator-count-label">Number of Translators, Editors, and Consultants</item>
    <item key="about.translators.translators-label">people</item>
    <item key="about.translators.affiliation-title">Contributors by affiliation</item>
    <item key="about.translators.affiliation-both-label">Affiliated with both Academia and Dharma Centers</item>
    <item key="about.translators.affiliation-academic-label">Affiliated with Academia</item>
    <item key="about.translators.affiliation-practitioner-label">Affiliated with Dharma Centers</item>
    <item key="about.translators.affiliation-label">of contributors</item>
    <item key="about.translators.region-title">Contributors by region</item>
    <item key="about.translators.region-label">of contributors</item>

    <!-- Sponsor a Sutra -->
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.header-img-src">#feSiteUrl/imgs/about-headers/sponsor-a-sutra.jpg</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.page-quote">“Sūtras teach us the Dharma. The sūtras are much more precious, much more important than
        the image of the Buddha.”</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.page-quote-author">H.E. Garchen Rinpoche</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.page-intro">
        <p class="intro">84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha aims to <strong>translate</strong> all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages,
            and <strong>make them available</strong> to everyone.</p>
        <p class="page-description">
            <strong>Sponsor A Sūtra</strong> is an opportunity to support the translation of a major text. Some of the long, important
            sūtras require a sizeable amount of funding to ensure the translation continues through to completion. Your support is needed
            for the successful translation of these texts.</p>
        <h2>How much does it cost to sponsor?</h2>
        <p>Sponsorship opportunities are now available in sections of:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>100 pages (US$25,000)</li>
            <li>150 pages (US$37,500)</li>
            <li>200 pages (US$50,000) or more.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>All donations are considered unrestricted contributions, enabling 84000 to carry out their goals of translation and global
            access efficiently and effectively. Please note that per sūtra suggested donation amounts are approximations only, and the
            actual cost may be greater or lesser when the overall costs of translation, editorial work, publication, and project management
            are taken into account.</p>
        <h2>How will the funds be used?</h2>
        <p>The funds will be used to cover the costs of translation, editorial work, publication, and project management. Please see <a href="#commsSiteUrl/about/work-flow">"What It Takes To Produce A Page of Translation"</a> to learn more about the many
            stages required for high quality translation.</p>
        <h2>Who can sponsor?</h2>
        <p>Anyone can make a sponsorship as an individual or family. Sponsorships can also be made in the name of a group (such as a
            company, sangha or temple), with the requirement that the group assigns a single contact person, and that one person will be
            designated as the sole recipient of any acknowledgement letters or gifts from 84000.</p>
        <h2>How will donors be acknowledged?</h2>
        <p>Donors will be recognized in the acknowledgements section of the text.</p>
        <p>In appreciation of your generous support, all the names and the dedication messages will be offered for prayers during the
            Dzongsar Monlam prayer festivals held biennially in Bodhgaya, India.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.donate-label">Donate online</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.text-list-title">Texts Available for Sponsorship</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.priority-title">Priority Texts</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.priority-description">The sponsorship, translation, and publication of texts in this section are considered a priority for 84000.</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.text-list-section-title">Sponsorship of up to #pageUpper pages (USD$#groupCost)</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.text-list-remainder-title">Sponsorship of more than #pageLower pages</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.part-icon-label-available">sponsorship opportunity available</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.part-icon-label-sponsored">sponsorship opportunity taken</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.reserved-label">Already reserved for sponsorship</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.sponsor-part-label">Sponsor a part</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.sponsor-whole-label">Sponsor the whole</item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.no-texts-of-type">There are currently no texts of this type proposed for sponsorship. </item>
    <item key="about.sponsor-a-sutra.footer">
        <p>For more information, please contact Huang Jing Rui, executive director, at: <a href="mailto:jingrui@84000.co">jingrui@84000.co</a>
        </p>
    </item>
    
    <!-- Progress panel widget -->
    <item key="widget.progress-panel.support-label">Join Us</item>
    <item key="widget.progress-panel.support-description">
        <p>With the help of our <a href="#readingRoomSiteUrl/about/sponsors.html">108 founding sponsors</a> and thousands of individual donors, we provide funding to the translators who are working to safeguard these important teachings for future generations.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="widget.progress-panel.kangyur-count-after-label">Total Kangyur Pages</item>
    <item key="widget.progress-panel.translation-count-after-label">Pages in Translation</item>
    <item key="widget.progress-panel.translated-count-after-label">Pages Translated</item>
    <item key="widget.progress-panel.published-count-after-label">Pages Published</item>
    
    <!-- Progress chart widget -->
    <item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-title-kangyur">25 Year Goal</item>
    <item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-description-kangyur">
        <p>To translate the complete teachings of the Buddha from Tibetan (Kangyur)</p>
        <ul class="list-unstyled">
            <li>Page Count: <strong>70,000</strong>
            </li>
            <li>Completed by: <strong>2035</strong>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </item>
    <!--<item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-subtitle-kangyur">70,000 pages</item>-->
    <!--<item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-description-kangyur">With your support, we are on track to meet our <strong>25 year goal</strong> to translate and make freely available the Buddhist Sūtras (Kangyur) by 2035.</item>-->
    <item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-title-combined">100 Year Goal</item>
    <item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-description-combined">
        <p>To translate the entire Tibetan Buddhist Canon (Kangyur and Tengyur)</p>
        <ul class="list-unstyled">
            <li>Page Count: <strong>231,800</strong>
            </li>
            <li>Completed by: <strong>2110</strong>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </item>
    <!--<item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-subtitle-combined">231,800 pages</item>-->
    <!--<item key="widget.progress-chart.tab-description-combined">Our <strong>100 year goal</strong> is the translation and free accessibility of all 231,800 pages of the Tibetan Buddhist Canon (Kangyur and Tengyur).</item>-->
    
    <!-- Download dana -->
    <item key="widget.download-dana.widget-title">Download Dāna</item>
    <item key="widget.download-dana.icon-label">You are downloading:</item>
    <item key="widget.download-dana.dana-description">
        <p>This is a free publication from 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, a non-profit organization sharing the gift of Buddhist wisdom with the world.</p>
        <p>The cultivation of generosity, or dāna—giving voluntarily with a view that something wholesome will come of it—is considered to
            be a fundamental Buddhist practice by all schools. The nature and quantity of the gift itself is often considered less
            important.</p>
    </item>
    <item key="widget.download-dana.donate-form-link">/download-dana</item>
    <item key="widget.download-dana.donate-form-link-label">Click here to make a dāna donation</item>
    
    <!-- Audio test -->
    <item key="about.audio-test.page-title">Audio test</item>

</texts>